A Finding Aid to the Elizabeth McCausland Papers, 1838-1995, bulk 1920-1960, in the Archives of American Art AAA.mccaeliz
Archives of American Art
- Elizabeth McCausland Material from the Estate of Berenice Abbott, 1920-1995; Series 15; 5.4 Linear feet Boxes 48-53
  Additional material belonging to Elizabeth McCausland and donated by the estate of Berenice Abbott include biographical material, business and personal correspondence, professional project files and writings, and printed materials, including reprints of critical essays and articles by McCausland. Biographical materials include additional curriculum vitae and a typescript address book of contacts. Correspondence includes invoices and letters from artists, including David Smith, Dorothy Leibes, and Jacob Lawrence; memos and invoices from her publishing agent, McIntosh and Otis Inc.; and correspondence from her brother and sister, Ross McCausland and Helen McCausland Kentor, regarding their personal lives and the family's estate. The subseries also contains 3 letters from Marsden Hartley addressed to Isgua Sanchez (Mrs. Patterson) McCan from Mexico dated from 1932.
  Project files consist of several book projects based on McCausland's research as an art critic, including Dilemma of Culture; Conversations with March, a fictional work illustrated by Charles Edward Buckley; a survey of artists and federal grant projects titled Artist in America; and drafts of a biography on Frank Kleinholz, which was commissioned by the artist. The general project files consist of research and miscellaneous material gathered on artists, subjects, and other potential writing projects. The teaching project files include teaching notes and outlines for art history classes McCausland taught in the 1940s, including a series of 14 lectures at the New School in 1946.
  Writings consist of drafts of articles, monographs, speeches, and reports authored by McCausland for publication in professional art history journals or for use in other professional contexts. Some drafts of creative works are also included in the subseries.
  Printed materials consist of articles, books, book reviews, monographs, exhibition catalog introductions, and pamphlets authored by McCausland, along with other miscellaneous clippings, clippings from the Springfield Republican, and a handful of other miscellaneous material. Intact copies of periodicals containing articles by McCausland, including Magazine of Art and Parnassus, have been retained in the collection.
  Additional materials related to this series can be found in Series 1-2, 7-8, and 10.
  This series is arranged as 10 subseries.
  15.1: Biographical Materials, 1942-1965
  15.2: Correspondence, 1920-1995
  15.3: Project Files, Artists in America, circa 1940-1961
  15.4: Project Files, Conversations with March, circa 1945-1963
  15.5: Project Files, Dilemma of Culture, circa 1935-1947
  15.6: Project Files, Frank Kleinholz, circa 1950-1964
  15.7: Project Files, General, circa 1917-1963
  15.8: Project Files, Teaching, 1942-1946
  15.9: Writings, circa 1939-1964
  15.10: Printed Material, circa 1931-1963
  The bulk of this series has been scanned. In some cases, exhibition catalogs and other publications have had their covers, title pages, and relevant pages scanned.
  - Biographical Materials, 1942-1965; 15.1
    - Address Book, circa 1955-1965 (Box 48, Folder 1)
    - Certificates, 1942-1964 (Box 48, Folder 2)
    - Curriculum Vitae, 1947-1957 (Box 48, Folder 3)
    - Memorabilia, 1948 (Box 48, Folder 4)
    - Photograph of Artwork, circa 1950-1960 (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1995; 15.2
    - A Miscellaneous, 1957-1963 (Box 48, Folder 6)
    - ACA Gallery, 1945-1963 (Box 48, Folder 7)
    - Adams, Helen, 1962-1963 (Box 48, Folder 8)
    - Adlow, Dorothy, 1960-1964 (Box 48, Folder 9)
    - Artist's Proof, 1961-1962 (Box 48, Folder 10)
    - B Miscellaneous, 1958-1964 (Box 48, Folder 11)
    - Babcock Galleries, 1958-1964 (Box 48, Folder 12)
    - Beam, Lura, 1957-1964 (Box 48, Folder 13)
    - Buckley, Charles Edward, 1952-1964 (Box 48, Folder 14)
    - Buffmire, Dorothy, 1958-1964 (Box 48, Folder 15)
    - C Miscellaneous, 1959-1963 (Box 48, Folder 16)
    - Chapelbrook Foundation, 1959-1962 (Box 48, Folder 17)
    - Charles-Percy Foundation, 1963 (Box 48, Folder 18)
    - Committee for the Vindication of Sacco and Vanzetti, 1960 (Box 48, Folder 19)
    - Cook, Waldo L. ( Springfield Republican), 1920-1963 (Box 48, Folder 20)
    - Cooper Union, 1947-1948 (Box 48, Folder 21)
    - Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1962-1964 (Box 48, Folder 22)
    - Cowdrey, Mary Bartlett, 1953-1956 (Box 48, Folder 23)
    - D Miscellaneous, 1958-1959 (Box 48, Folder 24)
    - Dickinson, Martha L. (Weyhe Gallery), 1953-1963 (Box 48, Folder 25)
    - Doctors, Regarding Hand Injury, 1962-1963 (Box 48, Folder 26)
    - E-F Miscellaneous, 1953-1962 (Box 48, Folder 27)
    - Ford Foundation, 1960-1964 (Box 48, Folder 28)
    - Fulton, W. Joseph, 1959-1964 (Box 48, Folder 29)
    - G Miscellaneous, 1957-1961 (Box 48, Folder 30)
    - H Miscellaneous, 1926-1967 (Box 48, Folder 31)
    - Haering, Ilene, 1958-1962 (Box 48, Folder 32)
    - Hartley, Marsden, 1932 (Box 48, Folder 33)
    - Hoopes, Donelson F. (Corcoran Gallery of Art), 1961-1964 (Box 48, Folder 34)
    - Housing, Regarding Apartments, 1937-1944 (Box 48, Folder 35)
    - International Association of Art Critics, 1956-1964 (Box 48, Folder 36)
    - Jaffe, Ella, 1961-1962 (Box 48, Folder 37)
    - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1959-1962 (Box 48, Folder 38)
    - K Miscellaneous, 1947-1960 (Box 48, Folder 39)
    - Kehaya, Dorian, 1950 (Box 48, Folder 40)
    - Kentnor, Helen McCausland, 1956-1995 (Box 48, Folder 41)
    - L Miscellaneous, 1953-1964 (Box 48, Folder 42)
      Includes correspondence from Jacob Lawrence
    - Lerner, Abe, 1947-1961 (Box 48, Folder 43)
    - Liebes, Dorothy, 1946-1947 (Box 48, Folder 44)
    - Long Beach Art Association, 1953-1954 (Box 48, Folder 45)
    - Lund, Gay and Harold, 1961-1964 (Box 48, Folder 46)
    - M Miscellaneous, 1954-1963 (Box 48, Folder 47)
    - Massachusetts Review, 1959-1961 (Box 48, Folder 48)
    - McCausland, Ross, 1941-1975 (Box 48, Folder 49-52)
    - McIntosh and Otis Inc. (Abbot, Mary), 1950-1965 (Box 48, Folder 53)
    - N Miscellaneous, 1958-1963 (Box 48, Folder 54)
    - New York Historical Society, 1955-1961 (Box 48, Folder 55)
    - O-P Miscellaneous, 1958-1961 (Box 48, Folder 56)
    - P.F. Collier and Son Corporation, 1959 (Box 48, Folder 57)
    - Paine Art Center, 1962 (Box 48, Folder 58)
    - Powell, Leslie, 1960-1961 (Box 48, Folder 59)
    - R Miscellaneous, 1959-1964 (Box 48, Folder 60)
    - Radcliffe Institute for Independent Study, 1960-1962 (Box 48, Folder 61)
    - S Miscellaneous, 1963 (Box 48, Folder 62)
      Includes a letter from Paul Strand
    - Shwachman, Irene, 1962-1963 (Box 48, Folder 63)
    - Smith, David, 1940 (Box 48, Folder 64)
    - U Miscellaneous, 1961 (Box 48, Folder 65)
    - University of Minnesota, University Press, 1957-1961 (Box 48, Folder 66-67)
    - W Miscellaneous, 1943-1963 (Box 48, Folder 68)
    - Whitney Museum, 1954-1961 (Box 48, Folder 69)
    - Cards, Birthday, circa 1960-1965 (Box 49, Folder 1)
    - Cards, Holiday (by surname), circa 1960-1970 (Box 49, Folder 2-3)
    - Cards, Holiday (no surname), circa 1960-1970 (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - Project Files, Artist in America, circa 1940-1961; 15.3
    - Project Overview, 1947-1961 (Box 49, Folder 5)
    - Artists Lists, circa 1943-1961 (Box 49, Folder 6)
    - Bibliography, circa 1940-1960 (Box 49, Folder 7-10)
    - Chapter Outlines, 1947 (Box 49, Folder 11)
    - Introduction, circa 1944 (Box 49, Folder 12)
    - Introduction and Chapter 1, 1947 (Box 49, Folder 13)
    - Chapter 1, circa 1944-1947 (Box 49, Folder 14)
    - Chapter 2 (draft), circa 1945-1960 (Box 49, Folder 15)
    - Chapter 2 (research), circa 1945-1960 (Box 49, Folder 16)
    - Chapter 3, circa 1945-1960 (Box 49, Folder 17)
    - Chapter 4, circa 1945-1960 (Box 49, Folder 18)
    - Chapter 5, circa 1945-1960 (Box 49, Folder 19)
    - Chapter 6, circa 1945-1965 (Box 49, Folder 20)
    - Chapter 7, circa 1945-1960 (Box 49, Folder 21)
    - Chapter 10, circa 1945-1960 (Box 49, Folder 22)
    - Notebook Index, A-I, circa 1943-1961 (Box 49, Folder 23)
    - Notebook Index, J-Z, circa 1943-1961 (Box 49, Folder 24)
    - Notebook, Table of Contents #1-5, circa 1943-1961 (Box 49, Folder 25)
    - Notebook, #1 (part 1 of 2), circa 1943-1961 (Box 49, Folder 26)
    - Notebook, #1 (part 2 of 2), circa 1943-1961 (Box 49, Folder 27)
    - Notebook, #2, circa 1943-1961 (Box 49, Folder 28)
    - Notebook, #3, circa 1943-1961 (Box 49, Folder 29)
    - Notebook, #4, circa 1943-1961 (Box 49, Folder 30)
    - Notebook, #5, circa 1943-1961 (Box 49, Folder 31)
    - Notebook, #6, circa 1943-1961 (Box 49, Folder 32)
    - Notebook, #7, circa 1943-1961 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - Notebook, #8, circa 1943-1961 (Box 50, Folder 2)
    - Notebook, #9, circa 1943-1961 (Box 50, Folder 3)
    - Research, Printed Material, circa 1936-1954 (Box 50, Folder 4)
    - Research, Photographs, circa 1955-1965 (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Research, Photographs of Artwork, circa 1955-1960 (Box 50, Folder 6)
  - Project Files, Conversations with March, circa 1945-1963; 15.4
    - Correspondence, Agents, 1951-1953 (Box 50, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, Buckley, Charles Edward, 1950-1953 (Box 50, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, Parties, circa 1950-1953 (Box 50, Folder 9)
    - Book Formatting, circa 1952-1955 (Box 50, Folder 10)
    - Book Illustrations, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 11)
    - Book Notes, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 12)
    - Book Resources, circa 1951-1963 (Box 50, Folder 13)
    - Draft, Chapter 1-3, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 14)
    - Draft, Chapter 1-22, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 15)
    - Draft, Chapter 1 - Spring Equinox, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 16)
    - Draft, Chapter 2 - On Liberty, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 17)
    - Draft, Chapter 3 - World Is Wide, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 18)
    - Draft, Chapter 4 - On Learning, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 19)
    - Draft, Chapter 5 - Spring Comes, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 20)
    - Draft, Chapter 6 - On Science, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 21)
    - Draft, Chapter 7 - Good Life, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 22)
    - Draft, Chapter 8 - Looking at Pictures, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 23)
    - Draft, Chapter 9 - Marches for March, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 24)
    - Draft, Chapter 10 - Rudolph on the Roof, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 25)
    - Draft, Chapter 11 - Birthday Cake, Birthday Cake, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 26)
    - Draft, Chapter 12 - March on the Machine, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 27)
    - Draft, Chapter 13 - Moths and Illusion, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 27)
    - Draft, Chapter 14 - Chapter 17, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 29)
    - Draft, Chapter 18 - Thanksgiving, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 30)
    - Draft, Chapter 19 - March to Moon, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 31)
    - Draft, Chapter 21 - Rights of Cats, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 32)
    - Draft, Chapter 22 - Adoption Day, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 33)
    - Photographs, circa 1952-1963 (Box 50, Folder 34)
  - Project Files, Dilemma of Culture, circa 1935-1947; 15.5
    - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 50, Folder 35-36)
    - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 50, Folder 37)
    - Chapter Outline, 1940 (Box 50, Folder 38)
    - Draft, "Frustration of Culture", circa 1939 (Box 50, Folder 39)
    - Research, Artists, circa 1935-1945 (Box 50, Folder 40)
    - Research, History, circa 1935-1945 (Box 50, Folder 41)
    - Research Proposal, Guggenheim, 1942 (Box 50, Folder 42)
  - Project Files, Frank Kleinholz, circa 1950-1964; 15.6
    - Correspondence, 1960-1964 (Box 50, Folder 43)
    - Book, First Draft, circa 1962 (Box 50, Folder 44)
    - Book, Second Draft, circa 1962 (Box 50, Folder 45)
    - Draft, Edits, circa 1963 (Box 50, Folder 46)
    - Draft, Notes, circa 1963 (Box 50, Folder 47)
    - Illustrations, circa 1960-1964 (Box 50, Folder 48)
    - Research, Artwork, 1962 (Box 50, Folder 49)
    - Research, Autobiography (handwritten), circa 1962 (Box 50, Folder 50)
    - Research, Autobiography (typescript), circa 1962 (Box 50, Folder 51)
    - Research, Biography/Chronology, circa 1962 (Box 50, Folder 52)
    - Research, Printed Material, circa 1950-1961 (Box 50, Folder 53)
  - Project Files, General, circa 1917-1963; 15.7
    - American Artists Group, circa 1917-1947 (Box 50, Folder 54)
    - Art 1942, Correspondence (Box 50, Folder 55)
    - Art 1942, Statement of Aims (Box 50, Folder 56)
    - Astor Diamond Necklace, circa 1940-1960 (Box 51, Folder 1-2)
    - Book Proposal, Evolution of American Art, 1913-1935, circa 1937 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Book Proposal, Giants in the Arts, circa 1950 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Daniel, Charles, 1951 (Box 51, Folder 5)
    - Dove, Arthur, 1954-1961 (Box 51, Folder 6)
    - Hahn, William, 1942 (Box 51, Folder 7)
    - Harnett, William M., 1939-1941 (Box 51, Folder 8)
    - Hartley, Marsden, 1949-1957 (Box 51, Folder 9)
    - Inness, George, 1957-1960 (Box 51, Folder 10)
    - Kollwitz, Kathe, circa 1941 (Box 51, Folder 11)
    - Levine, Jack, 1947 (Box 51, Folder 12)
    - Luks, George, 1961 (Box 51, Folder 13)
    - Maurer, Alfred, 1956-1963 (Box 51, Folder 14)
    - Museum of Modern Art, Exhibitions, 1938-1944 (Box 51, Folder 15)
    - Noble, John, 1949-1953 (Box 51, Folder 16)
    - Photography, circa 1933-1950 (Box 51, Folder 17)
    - Picture Research, circa 1940-1955 (Box 51, Folder 18)
    - Springfield Museum of Fine Arts, 1931-1935 (Box 51, Folder 19)
    - Whitney Museum, 1961 (Box 51, Folder 20)
  - Project Files, Teaching, 1942-1946; 15.8
    - Class Notes, American Art and American Life, 1946 (Box 51, Folder 21)
    - Class Notes, Art in the Modern World, 1943 (Box 51, Folder 22)
    - Class Notes, History of Art (syllabus), 1942-1944 (Box 51, Folder 23)
    - Class Notes, History of Art (additional materials), 1942-1944 (Box 51, Folder 24)
    - Class Notes, History of Art (department memos), 1943-1944 (Box 51, Folder 25)
    - Lecture Dates, 1944 (Box 51, Folder 26)
    - New School Lectures, #1-8, 1946 (Box 51, Folder 27)
    - New School Lectures, #9-14, 1946 (Box 51, Folder 28)
    - New School Lectures, Notes, circa 1946 (Box 51, Folder 29)
  - Writings, circa 1939-1964; 15.9
    - Creative, Play, circa 1947 (Box 51, Folder 30)
    - Creative, Poems, 1963-1964 (Box 51, Folder 31)
    - Creative, Reminiscences, circa 1935-1955 (Box 51, Folder 32)
    - Essay, "American Standard of Photography" (drafts 1-2), circa 1939 (Box 51, Folder 33)
    - Essay, "American Standard of Photography" (drafts 3-4), circa 1939 (Box 51, Folder 34)
    - Essay, "American Standard of Photography" (notes), circa 1939 (Box 51, Folder 35)
    - Essay, "Bringing Art and the Public Together", circa 1940-1955 (Box 51, Folder 36)
    - Essay, "Documentary Photography", circa 1945-1960 (Box 51, Folder 37)
    - Essay, "Feet", circa 1945-1960 (Box 51, Folder 38)
    - Essay, "Horizon for Photography", circa 1940 (Box 51, Folder 39)
    - Essay, "Oil Colors vs. Silver Salts", 1953-1954 (Box 51, Folder 40)
    - Essay, "State of the Artist", 1951 (Box 51, Folder 41)
    - Essay, "Story of Oil", circa 1957 (Box 51, Folder 42)
    - Essay, "Why Can't America Afford Art?", circa 1946 (Box 51, Folder 43)
    - Essays, On Photography, circa 1940-1955 (Box 51, Folder 44)
    - Monograph, Marsden Hartley (catalog), circa 1951 (Box 51, Folder 45)
    - Monograph, Marsden Hartley (essay), circa 1951 (Box 51, Folder 46)
    - Report, "On Artists in the United States", 1951-1952 (Box 51, Folder 47)
    - Speech, "Art and the Atom", 1947 (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Speech, "Art Patronage in the United States", 1945 (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - Speech, "Economic Base of Art", 1947 (Box 52, Folder 3)
    - Speech, "How the Matter Stands", 1947 (Box 52, Folder 4)
    - Speech, "Introducing Elisabeth Hoyt", 1947 (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - Speech, "Standards of Photographic Criticism", 1944 (Box 52, Folder 6)
  - Printed Material, circa 1931-1963; 15.10
    - Article, "Alchemy and the Artist: I. Rice Pereira", 1947 (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - Article, "Cooper Union", 1947 (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - Article, "George Inness and Thomas Eakins", 1940 (Box 52, Folder 9)
    - Article, "Johannes Gutenberg", 1937 (Box 52, Folder 10)
    - Article, "Portrait of a Photographer", 1938 (Box 52, Folder 11)
    - Article, "Research and Background Material for the Photographer", circa 1943 (Box 52, Folder 12)
    - Article, "Save the Arts Projects", 1937 (Box 52, Folder 13)
    - Article, "Social Art", 1938 (Box 52, Folder 14)
    - Article, "Trade Union Rears Its Artistic Head in Springfield", 1938 (Box 52, Folder 15)
    - Article, "Tradition and Marsden Hartley", 1962 (Box 52, Folder 16)
    - Article, "Use of Art in America", 1947 (Box 52, Folder 17)
    - Article, "Why Can't America Afford Art?", 1946 (Box 52, Folder 18)
    - Book, Art Professions in the United States, 1950 (Box 52, Folder 19)
    - Book Reviews on McCausland Publications, 1946-1952 (Box 52, Folder 20)
    - Bulletin, New York State Museum, On Edward Lamson Henry, 1945 (Box 52, Folder 21)
    - Clippings, By McCausland, 1937-1954 (Box 52, Folder 22)
    - Clippings on Art, circa 1923-1947 (Box 52, Folder 23)
    - Clippings on Art, Notebook (A-E), circa 1936-1947 (Box 52, Folder 24)
    - Clippings on Art, Notebook (F-M), circa 1936-1947 (Box 52, Folder 25)
    - Clippings on Art, Notebook (N-R), circa 1936-1947 (Box 52, Folder 26)
    - Clippings on Art, Notebook (S-Z), circa 1936-1947 (Box 52, Folder 27)
    - Clippings, Springfield Republican, 1931-1945 (Box 52, Folder 28-29)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, ACA Gallery, 1944-1946 (Box 52, Folder 30)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, Berkshire Museum, 1939 (Box 52, Folder 31)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, By Artist, 1945-1963 (Box 52, Folder 32)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, General, 1934-1938 (Box 52, Folder 33-34)
    - Monograph, Charles W. Hawthorne, 1947 (Box 52, Folder 35)
    - Monograph, David Burliuk, 1962 (Box 52, Folder 36)
    - Monograph, George Inness, 1946 (Box 52, Folder 37)
    - Monograph, John Whorf, circa 1940-1960 (Box 52, Folder 38)
    - Monograph, Marsden Hartley, 1952 (Box 52, Folder 39)
    - Pamphlet, Blue Menace, 1928 (Box 52, Folder 40)
    - Pamphlet, Printmakers, 1939 (Box 52, Folder 41)
    - Periodical, American Collector, 1945-1946 (Box 52, Folder 42)
    - Periodical, Art Digest, 1951 (Box 52, Folder 43)
    - Periodical, Antiques, 1955 (Box 52, Folder 44)
    - Periodical, Art in America, 1952, 1957 (Box 52, Folder 45)
    - Periodical, Artist's Proof, 1962 (Box 52, Folder 46)
    - Periodical, Arts and Architecture, 1946 (Box 52, Folder 47)
    - Periodical, Arts Magazine, 1961 (Box 52, Folder 48)
    - Periodical, College Art Journal, 1949, 1953 (Box 52, Folder 49)
    - Periodical, Magazine of Art, 1944-1945 (Box 52, Folder 50)
    - Periodical, Magazine of Art, 1946-1951 (Box 53, Folder 1-2)
    - Periodical, Nation, 1955 (Box 53, Folder 3)
    - Periodical, Panorama, 1945 (Box 53, Folder 5)
    - Periodical, New Currents, 1944 (Box 53, Folder 4)
    - Periodical, Parnassus, 1937-1940 (Box 53, Folder 6-9)
    - Periodical, Photo Technique, 1941 (Box 53, Folder 10)
    - Periodical, University of Nebraska Galleries, 1954 (Box 53, Folder 11)
    - Printed Press, circa 1931-1933 (Box 53, Folder 12)
    - Program, 1952 (Box 53, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1921-1963 (Box 53, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Material, Theater Programs, circa 1963 (Box 53, Folder 15)